<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving
and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
  <front>
    <article-meta>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Regional growth, convergence, and spatial spillovers in
India:</article-title>
        <subtitle>A view from outer space</subtitle>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0001-7978-2815</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Mendez</surname>
            <given-names>Carlos</given-names>
          </name>
          <string-name>Carlos Mendez</string-name>
          <email>carlosmendez777@gmail.com</email>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">a</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor-1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-3844-1197</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Kabiraj</surname>
            <given-names>Sujana</given-names>
          </name>
          <string-name>Sujana Kabiraj</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2">b</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-8888-1234</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Jiaqi</given-names>
          </name>
          <string-name>Jiaqi Li</string-name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">a</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff-1">
        <institution-wrap>
          <institution>Nagoya University</institution>
        </institution-wrap>
        <city>Nagoya</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff-2">
        <institution-wrap>
          <institution>Shiv Nadar University</institution>
        </institution-wrap>
        <city>Greater Noida</city>
        <country>India</country>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor-1">carlosmendez777@gmail.com</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <history/>
      <abstract>
        <p>Using satellite nighttime light data as proxy for economic activity,
Chanda and Kabiraj (2020, World Development) studied regional growth and
convergence across 520 districts in India. This article builds on their
work by confirming and extending their main findings in three fronts.
First, we illustrate regional convergence patterns using an interactive
web-based tool for satellite image visualization. Second, we assess the
degree of spatial dependence in their main econometric specification.
Third, we employ a spatial Durbin model to measure the role of spatial
spillovers in the convergence process. Our results indicate that spatial
spillovers significantly increase the speed of regional convergence.
Overall, the results emphasize the role of spatial dependence in
regional convergence through the lens of satellite imagery, interactive
visualizations, and spillover modeling.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <kwd>Regional luminosity</kwd>
        <kwd>Satellite nighttime lights</kwd>
        <kwd>Regional convergence</kwd>
        <kwd>Spatial spillovers</kwd>
        <kwd>Spatial Durbin model</kwd>
        <kwd>India</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Regional economic growth and convergence are key concerns in
  developing countries, particularly in large federal states like India
  where spatial inequalities can threaten social cohesion and political
  stability. However, studying regional convergence patterns in
  developing countries has been historically challenging due to limited
  availability of consistent economic data at subnational administrative
  levels. The emergence of satellite nighttime light data as a proxy for
  economic activity has created new opportunities to analyze regional
  growth dynamics at granular geographic scales.</p>
      <p>In an important contribution, Chanda and Kabiraj
  (<xref alt="2020" rid="ref-chanda_kabiraj_district_convergence" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>)
  leveraged nighttime light data to document evidence of regional
  convergence across 520 districts in India between 1996 and 2010. Their
  analysis showed that poorer districts grew faster than richer ones
  during this period, suggesting a gradual reduction in spatial
  inequalities. However, their econometric approach did not account for
  potential spatial spillovers in the convergence process—the
  possibility that a district’s growth trajectory might be influenced
  not only by its own initial conditions but also by those of its
  neighbors.</p>
      <p>In this context, this paper confirms and extends the study of
  Chanda and Kabiraj
  (<xref alt="2020" rid="ref-chanda_kabiraj_district_convergence" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>)
  in three key methodological directions. First, we develop an
  interactive web-based visualization tool that allows researchers to
  dynamically explore spatial and temporal patterns in the nighttime
  light data. This tool facilitates the identification of converging
  regions and growth hotspots that may be difficult to detect in static
  representations. Second, we formally test for spatial dependence in
  both the dependent and independent variables of the convergence
  equations, highlighting that spatial autocorrelation is an inherent
  feature of satellite data and the regional convergence process. Third,
  we employ a spatial Durbin model that explicitly accounts for spatial
  spillovers, quantifying how neighborhood effects influence the speed
  of regional convergence.</p>
      <p>Our results yield three main findings that advance our
  understanding of regional convergence in India. First, interactive
  visualization tools reveal clear spatial patterns in both the initial
  distribution and subsequent growth of nighttime lights. Second, formal
  tests of spatial dependence indicate that district-level economic
  trajectories are not independent of their neighbors. Third, accounting
  for spatial spillovers through the spatial Durbin model shows that the
  total convergence effect is substantially larger than previous
  non-spatial estimates would suggest. Specifically, spatial spillovers
  appear to accelerate the convergence process by creating additional
  channels through which lagging regions can catch up.</p>
      <p>These findings have important implications for both research
  methodology and policy design. Methodologically, they demonstrate that
  conventional non-spatial approaches may significantly underestimate
  the speed of regional convergence by failing to account for
  inter-district spillovers. From a policy perspective, they suggest
  that the benefits of place-based development interventions may extend
  beyond target districts through spatial multiplier effects,
  potentially increasing their cost-effectiveness. The results also
  highlight the value of new data sources and methodological tools in
  advancing our understanding of regional economic dynamics in
  developing countries.</p>
      <p>The rest of this article is organized as follows. Section 2
  provides an overview of the data and methods, describing our use of
  nighttime light data as a proxy for economic activity and introducing
  the spatial Durbin model that forms the basis of our empirical
  strategy. We also detail our methodological extensions related to
  interactive visualizations, spatial dependence testing, and spillover
  modeling. Section 3 presents our empirical results, beginning with an
  interactive exploration of regional convergence patterns, followed by
  formal tests of spatial dependence, and concluding with estimates of
  direct and indirect convergence effects from the spatial Durbin model.
  Finally, Section 4 offers some concluding remarks.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="data-and-methods">
      <title>Data and methods</title>
      <sec id="data-nightlights-as-a-proxy-for-economic-activity">
        <title>Data: Nightlights as a proxy for economic activity</title>
        <p>One of the key challenges in studying economic growth in
    developing countries like India is the limited availability and
    reliability of data on aggregate economic activity at finer
    administrative levels beyond the state level. To address this issue,
    a growing body of literature, pioneered by Henderson, Storeygard,
    and Weil
    (<xref alt="2012" rid="ref-henderson_storeygard_weil_lights" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>),
    has utilized satellite nighttime light data as a proxy for economic
    activity at sub-national levels.</p>
        <p>Nightlight data has been widely used to investigate economic
    growth and convergence across national and sub-national regions in
    various countries. For instance, Adhikari and Dhital
    (<xref alt="2020" rid="ref-adhikari_dhital_decentralization" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>)
    examine the impact of decentralization on regional convergence using
    nightlight data, while Pinkovskiy and Sala-i-Martin
    (<xref alt="2016" rid="ref-pinkovskiy_salaimartin_lights_poverty" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>)
    use nightlight data to adjudicate between national accounts and
    household surveys, finding that national accounts better capture
    aggregate economic growth. Similarly, Lessmann and Seidel
    (<xref alt="2017" rid="ref-lessmann_seidel_regional_inequality" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>)
    leverage nightlight data to estimate GDP per capita and income
    inequality globally. More broadly, Gennaioli et al.
    (<xref alt="2014" rid="ref-gennaioli_etal_growth_regions" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>)
    study regional convergence using per capita income data from 1,528
    subnational regions across 83 countries, finding a convergence rate
    of about 2% per year.</p>
        <p>Nightlight data has been widely utilized in India across various
    contexts. For example, Cook and Shah
    (<xref alt="2022" rid="ref-cook_shah_nregs" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>)
    use nightlight data to analyze the impact of public welfare
    programs, while Jha and Talathi
    (<xref alt="2021" rid="ref-jha_talathi_colonial_india" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>)
    examine the effects of colonial institutions, and Chanda and Cook
    (<xref alt="2022" rid="ref-chanda_cook_demonetization" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>)
    investigate the impact of demonetization. Beyer, Jain, and Sinha
    (<xref alt="2021" rid="ref-beyer_jain_sinha_covid" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>)
    employ nightlight data to study the effects of COVID-19. In the
    context of convergence studies, Chakravarty and Dehejia
    (<xref alt="2019" rid="ref-chakravarty_dehejia_gst" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>)
    document significant regional disparities in India using nightlight
    data and caution that GST may further exacerbate them, while
    (<xref alt="Chanda and Kabiraj 2020" rid="ref-chanda_kabiraj_district_convergence" ref-type="bibr">Chanda
    and Kabiraj 2020</xref>) highlights district-level convergence.</p>
        <p>Our study draws inspiration from
    (<xref alt="Chanda and Kabiraj 2020" rid="ref-chanda_kabiraj_district_convergence" ref-type="bibr">Chanda
    and Kabiraj 2020</xref>). Following their approach, we use the per
    capita growth in nightlights as the dependent variable and the
    initial nightlights per capita as the primary variable of interest.
    These variables are derived from nightlight data released by the
    National Geophysical Data Center (NGDC), based on observations from
    the DMSP/OLS satellites spanning the period from 1996 to 2010. To
    mitigate the issue of top-coding in light data, the NGDC released
    “radiance-calibrated” nighttime lights for eight specific years
    within this period. This dataset employs high magnification settings
    for low-light regions and low magnification settings for brightly
    lit areas. For this study, we utilize the “radiance-calibrated”
    nighttime lights data.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">1</xref></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="modeling-regional-convergence">
        <title>Modeling regional convergence</title>
        <p>In neoclassical growth models, such as the Solow model, it is
    argued that the per capita growth rate should be negatively
    correlated with a region’s initial endowment primarily due to
    diminishing returns to capital. Specifically, poorer regions,
    assuming similar technology and preferences, are expected to
    experience higher growth rates compared to their wealthier
    counterparts. Consequently, over the long run, regions with similar
    characteristics should converge to a common steady state. We would
    like to explore such convergence (denoted by
    <bold><inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[\beta]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>-convergence</bold>)
    employing a Barro-style growth regressions framework. Equation (1)
    analyzes absolute convergence.</p>
        <p>
          <styled-content id="eq-matrix-form-abs">
            <disp-formula>
              <alternatives>
                <tex-math><![CDATA[
    \boldsymbol{g_t} =  \beta_1 \boldsymbol{x_{t-1}} +  \boldsymbol{\varepsilon_t}
     \qquad(1)]]></tex-math>
                <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>𝐠</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>𝐭</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>𝐱</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>𝐭</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mo mathvariant="bold">−</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mn>𝟏</mml:mn>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>𝛆</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>𝐭</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mspace width="2.0em"/>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo stretchy="true" form="prefix">(</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                      <mml:mo stretchy="true" form="postfix">)</mml:mo>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:math>
              </alternatives>
            </disp-formula>
          </styled-content>
        </p>
        <p>where <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[\boldsymbol{g_t}]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi>𝐠</mml:mi><mml:mi>𝐭</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    represents an <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[N\text{-by-}1]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mtext mathvariant="normal">-by-</mml:mtext><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    vector of observations on NTL growth for each of the
    <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[N]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    regions over the period <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[t]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    and <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[\boldsymbol{x_{t-1}}]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi>𝐱</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>𝐭</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>𝟏</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    represents an <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[N\text{-by-}1]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mtext mathvariant="normal">-by-</mml:mtext><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    vector of observations on the initial (log) level of NTL. The scalar
    <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[\beta_1]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    is a regression coefficient that indicates the direction and
    strength of regional convergence. Finally,
    <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[\boldsymbol{\varepsilon_t}]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi>𝛆</mml:mi><mml:mi>𝐭</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    represents a vector of idiosyncratic error terms.</p>
        <p>While absolute convergence implies that districts converge to a
    common steady state, regions may differ in various aspects such as
    geography, socio-economic conditions, and policy implementation. To
    account for these differences, we include state dummies in our
    analysis to examine whether heterogeneity in state-specific
    institutions and policies influences the rate of convergence.
    Additionally, we control for the initial share of unlit pixels in
    districts to address any potential under-coding in nightlights
    data.</p>
        <p>To further explore the determinants of district-level growth
    rates, we incorporate a range of geo-climatic controls alongside
    initial district-specific conditions related to demographics, human
    capital, and infrastructure.
    <xref alt="Equation 1" rid="eq-matrix-form-abs">Equation 1</xref>
    explores conditional convergence.</p>
        <p>
          <styled-content id="eq-matrix-form-cond">
            <disp-formula>
              <alternatives>
                <tex-math><![CDATA[
    \boldsymbol{g_t} =  \beta_1 \boldsymbol{x_{t-1}} + \boldsymbol{X_t} \boldsymbol{\alpha}  + \boldsymbol{\varepsilon_t}
     \qquad(2)]]></tex-math>
                <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>𝐠</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>𝐭</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>𝐱</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>𝐭</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mo mathvariant="bold">−</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mn>𝟏</mml:mn>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>𝐗</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>𝐭</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>𝛂</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>𝛆</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>𝐭</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mspace width="2.0em"/>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo stretchy="true" form="prefix">(</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
                      <mml:mo stretchy="true" form="postfix">)</mml:mo>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:math>
              </alternatives>
            </disp-formula>
          </styled-content>
        </p>
        <p>Here, the matrix <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[\boldsymbol{X_t}]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi>𝐗</mml:mi><mml:mi>𝐭</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    is a <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[N\text{-by-}k]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mtext mathvariant="normal">-by-</mml:mtext><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    collection of observations on control variables for each region. The
    vector <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[\boldsymbol{\alpha}]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:mi>𝛂</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>,
    with dimensions <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[k \times 1]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>,
    captures the regression coefficients for these variables. The
    control variables are listed in Table A.1 in Chanda and Kabiraj
    (<xref alt="2020" rid="ref-chanda_kabiraj_district_convergence" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="interactive-spatial-visualizations">
        <title>Interactive spatial visualizations</title>
        <p>Interactive visualizations of nighttime lights imagery offer
    distinct methodological advantages over static representations,
    particularly when analyzing temporal and spatial heterogeneity in
    economic activity. The dynamic nature of these visualizations
    enables researchers to simultaneously examine multiple dimensions of
    the data, including temporal variations in light intensity, the
    spatial distribution of economic activity, and the relationship
    between nighttime lights and other georeferenced variables. This
    interactivity is especially valuable when investigating economic
    phenomena that exhibit significant spatial and temporal variation,
    such as urbanization patterns, economic shocks, or regional
    development disparities. The ability to dynamically adjust
    visualization parameters, such as temporal ranges, spatial scales,
    and light intensity thresholds, allows for more nuanced exploration
    of economic patterns that might be obscured in static
    representations.</p>
        <p>Google Earth Engine (GEE) substantially reduces the computational
    and technical barriers to creating such interactive visualizations,
    offering a particularly advantageous platform for economic research
    utilizing nighttime lights data. The platform’s browser-based
    integrated development environment facilitates the creation of
    interactive web applications without requiring extensive
    infrastructure or specialized software installation. This capability
    is especially valuable for reproducible research, as it enables the
    development of web applications that can be shared with other
    researchers or stakeholders, allowing them to interact with the data
    and verify findings independently. The platform’s ability to handle
    large-scale geospatial computations server-side, combined with its
    extensive catalog of pre-processed nighttime lights datasets,
    including the DMSP-OLS and VIIRS collections, significantly
    streamlines the workflow from raw data to interactive visualization.
    This computational efficiency is particularly beneficial when
    analyzing long time series or large geographic areas, which would be
    computationally intensive using traditional desktop-based
    approaches.</p>
        <p>Interactive visualizations of nighttime lights data are
    particularly instrumental in identifying and analyzing patterns of
    regional convergence in luminosity, providing visual insights into
    economic convergence processes. Through dynamic visualization tools,
    researchers can track the evolution of light intensity across
    regions over time, effectively identifying areas that exhibit
    catch-up growth patterns - where initially dim regions progressively
    converge toward the luminosity levels of their brighter
    counterparts.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="spatial-dependence-testing">
        <title>Spatial dependence testing</title>
        <p>The analysis of regional convergence using nighttime light data
    requires explicit consideration of spatial dependence patterns
    across Indian districts. To formally test and account for such
    spatial relationships, we employ the global Moran’s I test and
    applied to the main variables of the convergence
    <xref alt="Equation 2" rid="eq-matrix-form-cond">Equation 2</xref> .
    The Moran’s I test quantifies the degree of spatial autocorrelation
    among geographic units and can be expressed as:</p>
        <p><disp-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[
    I=\frac{\sum_i \Sigma_j w_{i j} z_i \cdot z_j /\sum_i \Sigma_j w_{i j}}{\Sigma_i z_i^2 / n}
    ]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mi>Σ</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>/</mml:mi><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mi>Σ</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>Σ</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>/</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula>
    where <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[z_i]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    represents the deviation of observation
    <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[i]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    from the mean, and <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[w_{ij}]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    denotes the spatial weight between units
    <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[i]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    and <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[j]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>.
    The Moran statistic can range from -1 to +1, with positive values
    indicating spatial clustering and negative values suggesting spatial
    dispersion.</p>
        <p>The specification of the spatial weights matrix
    <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[\mathbf{W}]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:mi>𝐖</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    is crucial for capturing the underlying spatial structure. We
    primarily employ a Queen contiguity matrix defined as:</p>
        <p><disp-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[
    \mathbf{W}=\left[\begin{array}{ccccc}
    w_{11} & w_{12} & w_{13} & \cdots & w_{1 \mathrm{n}} \\
    w_{21} & w_{22} & w_{23} & \cdots & w_{2 \mathrm{n}} \\
    \vdots & \vdots & \vdots & w_{\mathrm{ij}} & \vdots \\
    w_{\mathrm{n} 1} & w_{\mathrm{n} 2} & w_{\mathrm{n} 3} & \cdots & w_{\mathrm{nn}}
    \end{array}\right]
    ]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>𝐖</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true" form="prefix">[</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="center" style="text-align: center"><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="center" style="text-align: center"><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="center" style="text-align: center"><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mn>13</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="center" style="text-align: center"><mml:mi>⋯</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="center" style="text-align: center"><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="center" style="text-align: center"><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mn>21</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="center" style="text-align: center"><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="center" style="text-align: center"><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mn>23</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="center" style="text-align: center"><mml:mi>⋯</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="center" style="text-align: center"><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="center" style="text-align: center"><mml:mi>⋮</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="center" style="text-align: center"><mml:mi>⋮</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="center" style="text-align: center"><mml:mi>⋮</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="center" style="text-align: center"><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="center" style="text-align: center"><mml:mi>⋮</mml:mi></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="center" style="text-align: center"><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="center" style="text-align: center"><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="center" style="text-align: center"><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="center" style="text-align: center"><mml:mi>⋯</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="center" style="text-align: center"><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo stretchy="true" form="postfix">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula>
    where <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[w_{ij}=1]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    for districts sharing either a border or vertex and 0 otherwise.
    Following standard practice, we row-normalize the weights
    matrix.</p>
        <p>The detection of significant spatial dependence would justify the
    use of spatial econometric techniques. In particular, Ertur and Koch
    (<xref alt="2007" rid="ref-ertur_koch_spatial_growth" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>)
    and Fischer
    (<xref alt="2011" rid="ref-fischer_spatial_mrw" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>)
    argue that the spatial Durbin model can properly account for spatial
    spillovers in the convergence process. This methodological choice
    allows us to distinguish between direct effects of district
    characteristics and indirect effects operating through spatial
    channels.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="spatial-spillover-modeling">
        <title>Spatial spillover modeling</title>
        <p>Our spatial spillover modeling builds upon the spatial Solow
    growth model developed by Ertur and Koch
    (<xref alt="2007" rid="ref-ertur_koch_spatial_growth" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>)
    and Fischer
    (<xref alt="2011" rid="ref-fischer_spatial_mrw" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>),
    which extends the traditional Solow framework to account for
    technological interdependence across regions. The model considers an
    economy of <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[N]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    subnational regions, each characterized by a Cobb-Douglas production
    function with constant returns to scale:</p>
        <p>
          <styled-content id="eq-production">
            <disp-formula>
              <alternatives>
                <tex-math><![CDATA[
    Y_{i t}=A_{i t} K_{i t}^{\alpha_{K}} H_{i t}^{\alpha_{H}} L_{i t}^{1-\alpha_{K} -\alpha_{H}}
     \qquad(3)]]></tex-math>
                <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>Y</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:msubsup>
                      <mml:mi>K</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>K</mml:mi>
                      </mml:msub>
                    </mml:msubsup>
                    <mml:msubsup>
                      <mml:mi>H</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>H</mml:mi>
                      </mml:msub>
                    </mml:msubsup>
                    <mml:msubsup>
                      <mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                        <mml:msub>
                          <mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>K</mml:mi>
                        </mml:msub>
                        <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                        <mml:msub>
                          <mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi>H</mml:mi>
                        </mml:msub>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msubsup>
                    <mml:mspace width="2.0em"/>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo stretchy="true" form="prefix">(</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
                      <mml:mo stretchy="true" form="postfix">)</mml:mo>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:math>
              </alternatives>
            </disp-formula>
          </styled-content>
        </p>
        <p>where <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[Y_{it}]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    represents output, <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[K_{it}]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    physical capital, <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[H_{it}]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    human capital, <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[L_{it}]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    labor force, and <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[A_{it}]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    the level of technological knowledge for region
    <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[i]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    at time <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[t]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>.
    The parameters <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[\alpha_K]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    and <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[\alpha_H]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    denote the output elasticities with respect to physical and human
    capital, respectively. A key innovation of this framework is the
    modeling of technological knowledge, which incorporates both
    internal and external factors:</p>
        <p>
          <styled-content id="eq-technology">
            <disp-formula>
              <alternatives>
                <tex-math><![CDATA[
    A_{i t}=\Omega_{t} k_{i t}^{\theta} h_{i t}^{\phi} \prod_{j \neq i}^{N} A_{j t}^{\rho W_{i j}}
     \qquad(4)]]></tex-math>
                <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:msubsup>
                      <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>θ</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msubsup>
                    <mml:msubsup>
                      <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msubsup>
                    <mml:munderover>
                      <mml:mo>∏</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mo>≠</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
                    </mml:munderover>
                    <mml:msubsup>
                      <mml:mi>A</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                      </mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi>
                        <mml:msub>
                          <mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:msub>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msubsup>
                    <mml:mspace width="2.0em"/>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo stretchy="true" form="prefix">(</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
                      <mml:mo stretchy="true" form="postfix">)</mml:mo>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:math>
              </alternatives>
            </disp-formula>
          </styled-content>
        </p>
        <p>This specification captures three distinct components of
    technological progress:</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>An exogenous component (<inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[\Omega_t]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>)
        representing the common stock of knowledge across regions</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>An embodied component (<inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[k_{i t}^{\theta} h_{i t}^{\phi}]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>)
        reflecting technology embedded in physical and human capital per
        worker</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>A spatial component (<inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[\prod_{j \neq i}^{N} A_{j t}^{\rho W_{i j}}]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∏</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>≠</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>)
        capturing technological interdependence between regions</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p>Based on this theoretical framework, Ertur and Koch
    (<xref alt="2007" rid="ref-ertur_koch_spatial_growth" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>)
    derived a spatial panel Durbin model that for regional spillovers
    across economies. Their model can be compactly written in matrix
    notation as:</p>
        <p>
          <styled-content id="eq-matrix_form">
            <disp-formula>
              <alternatives>
                <tex-math><![CDATA[
    \boldsymbol{g_t} =  \beta_1 \boldsymbol{x_{t-1}} + \boldsymbol{X_t} \boldsymbol{\alpha} + \beta_2 \boldsymbol{W} \boldsymbol{x_{t-1}} + \boldsymbol{W} \boldsymbol{X_t} \boldsymbol{\gamma} + \lambda \boldsymbol{W} \boldsymbol{g_t}  + \boldsymbol{\varepsilon_t}
     \qquad(5)]]></tex-math>
                <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>𝐠</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>𝐭</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>𝐱</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>𝐭</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mo mathvariant="bold">−</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mn>𝟏</mml:mn>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>𝐗</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>𝐭</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>𝛂</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>𝐖</mml:mi>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>𝐱</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mi>𝐭</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mo mathvariant="bold">−</mml:mo>
                        <mml:mn>𝟏</mml:mn>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mi>𝐖</mml:mi>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>𝐗</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>𝐭</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>𝛄</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>𝐖</mml:mi>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>𝐠</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>𝐭</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>𝛆</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mi>𝐭</mml:mi>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mspace width="2.0em"/>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:mo stretchy="true" form="prefix">(</mml:mo>
                      <mml:mn>5</mml:mn>
                      <mml:mo stretchy="true" form="postfix">)</mml:mo>
                    </mml:mrow>
                  </mml:mrow>
                </mml:math>
              </alternatives>
            </disp-formula>
          </styled-content>
        </p>
        <p>In this model, <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[\boldsymbol{g_t}]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi>𝐠</mml:mi><mml:mi>𝐭</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    represents an <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[N\text{-by-}1]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mtext mathvariant="normal">-by-</mml:mtext><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    vector of observations on NTL growth for each of the
    <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[N]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    regions over the period <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[t]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    and <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[\boldsymbol{x_{t-1}}]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi>𝐱</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>𝐭</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>𝟏</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    represents an <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[N\text{-by-}1]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mtext mathvariant="normal">-by-</mml:mtext><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    vector of observations on the initial (log) level of NTL. The scalar
    <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[\beta_1]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    is a regression coefficient that indicates the direction and
    strength of regional convergence. The matrix
    <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[\boldsymbol{X_t}]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi>𝐗</mml:mi><mml:mi>𝐭</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    is a <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[N\text{-by-}k]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mtext mathvariant="normal">-by-</mml:mtext><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    collection of observations on control variables for each region. The
    vector <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[\boldsymbol{\alpha}]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:mi>𝛂</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>,
    with dimensions <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[k \times 1]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>,
    captures the regression coefficients for these variables.
    Additionally, <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[\boldsymbol{WX_t}]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>𝐖</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>𝐗</mml:mi><mml:mi>𝐭</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    denotes a <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[N \times k]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    matrix of spatially lagged observations, composed of a linear
    combination of neighboring values for the variables of interest in
    each region. The vector <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[\boldsymbol{\gamma}]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:mi>𝛄</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    represents the regression coefficients associated with these spatial
    lags. The terms <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[\boldsymbol{W} \boldsymbol{x_{t-1}}]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>𝐖</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>𝐱</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>𝐭</mml:mi><mml:mo mathvariant="bold">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>𝟏</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    and <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[\boldsymbol{W} \boldsymbol{g_t}]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>𝐖</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>𝐠</mml:mi><mml:mi>𝐭</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    refer to <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[N\text{-by-}1]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mtext mathvariant="normal">-by-</mml:mtext><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    vectors capturing the spatial lags of initial (log) level of NTL,
    and the NTL growth, respectively. Finally,
    <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[\boldsymbol{\varepsilon_t}]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mi>𝛆</mml:mi><mml:mi>𝐭</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
    represents a vector of idiosyncratic error terms.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="regional-convergence-an-interactive-exploration-from-outer-space">
        <title>Regional convergence: An interactive exploration from outer
    space</title>
        <p>Before presenting the regression results, we conducted three
    exercises to visually illustrate the concepts of growth and
    convergence in nightlights. Firstly, we created an interactive map
    of India displaying regional luminosity levels for 1996 and
    2010.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2">2</xref> Secondly, we examine
    absolute convergence by constructing a scatterplot that depicts the
    relationship between per capita growth rates in nightlights
    (1996–2010) and the initial per capita nightlight levels (1996) at
    the district level. Finally, we used case studies to emphasize the
    nightlight growth that occurred during our study period. Focusing on
    some of the poorest regions in the country, we demonstrate an
    increase in nighttime lights that aligns with our convergence
    hypothesis.</p>
        <fig id="fig-map">
          <caption>
            <p>Figure 1: Regional luminosity in India: 1996 vs 2010
      Notes: The unit of measurement for Nighttime Light (NTL)
      luminosity TBA. Interactive web application available at
      https://bit.ly/india-rc-ntl . Source: Pre-processed luminosity
      images are from the Earth Observation Group TBA.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="images/luminosity_map.png"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Figure 1 presents static maps (captured from our interactive
    maps) of luminosity for our boundary years (1996 and 2010), using
    the same index scale for comparison. The maps show a noticeable
    increase in brightness across most parts of the country in 2010.
    Since nightlights serve as a proxy for economic activity, this
    increase in luminosity reflects economic growth over the period.
    Figure 2 illustrates the relationship between per capita growth in
    nightlights and initial per capita nightlight levels. The scatter
    plot reveals a clear inverse relationship, indicating a
    <inline-formula><alternatives><tex-math><![CDATA[\beta]]></tex-math><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline"><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>-convergence
    rate of 2% consistent with Barro’s “Iron Law” of convergence.</p>
        <fig id="fig-map2">
          <caption>
            <p>Figure 2: Some illustrative examples of regional
      convergence Notes: The unit of measurement for Nighttime Light
      (NTL) luminosity TBA. Interactive web application available at
      https://bit.ly/india-rc-ntl . Source: Pre-processed luminosity
      images are from the Earth Observation Group TBA.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="images/luminosity_map2.png"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Next, we examine case studies of three economically disadvantaged
    states in India to illustrate their growth patterns over the study
    period. Among these, Bihar is the poorest, with a per capita income
    at 39.2% of the national average, while Uttar Pradesh and
    Chhattisgarh have per capita incomes of 43.8% and 52.3% of the
    national average,
    respectively.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3">3</xref> Figure 3
    displays the change in luminosity in these three states during our
    study period. Although these states remain among the poorest, there
    is a noticeable increase in luminosity over the course of the
    study.</p>
        <fig id="fig-convergence">
          <caption>
            <p>Figure 3: Regional luminosity convergence across
      districts in India Note: See Regional convergence notebook for
      source code. Source: Data from Chanda and Kabiraj
      (2000).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files/figure-jats/notebooks-c02_regional_convergence_sc-fig-convergence-output-2.png"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="spatial-dependence-is-a-feature-of-the-convergence-process">
        <title>Spatial dependence is a feature of the convergence
    process</title>
        <p>In this study, the spatial lag terms of luminosity per capita
    growth and initial luminosity per capita are computed by applying
    the Queen contiguity weight matrix. FigureX visually presents the
    relationship between local luminosity per capita growth rate and
    initial luminosity per capita and its spatial lag term,
    respectively. The strong positive spatial correlations observed
    between the variables and their neighboring regions suggest that
    regional convergence is not an isolated phenomenon, but rather a
    process intrinsically shaped by the influence of adjacent regions.
    The Moran’s I values of 0.644 and 0.739 for the variables, coupled
    with a statistically significant spatial autocorrelation in the
    error term, underscore the critical importance of spatial dependence
    in convergence research. These findings demonstrate that spatial
    interactions profoundly influence the convergence process, rendering
    it imperative to incorporate spatial effects in empirical
    analyses.</p>
        <p>This is a new figure.</p>
        <fig id="fig-dependence-initial">
          <caption>
            <p>Figure 4: Spatial dependence in the initial level of
      luminosity Note: See Regional convergence notebook for source
      code. Source: Data from Chanda and Kabiraj (2000).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files/figure-jats/notebooks-c03_spatial_dependence_lisa-fig-dependence-initial-output-1.png"/>
        </fig>
        <p>This is another new figure.</p>
        <fig id="fig-dependence-growth">
          <caption>
            <p>Figure 5: Spatial dependence in the growth rate of
      luminosity Note: See Regional convergence notebook for source
      code. Source: Data from Chanda and Kabiraj (2000).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files/figure-jats/notebooks-c03_spatial_dependence_lisa-fig-dependence-growth-output-1.png"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="spatial-spillovers-accelerate-regional-convergence">
        <title>Spatial spillovers accelerate regional convergence</title>
        <p>The regression results of
    <xref alt="Table 1" rid="tbl-models">Table 1</xref> provide evidence
    of both unconditional and conditional convergence across districts
    in India, with both conventional OLS and spatial econometric
    approaches indicating significant negative relationships between
    initial luminosity levels and subsequent growth rates. The direct
    effects, representing within-district convergence, remain remarkably
    stable across specifications, ranging from -0.020 to -0.026. This
    consistency across different model specifications and estimation
    methods provides evidence that poorer districts are indeed catching
    up to their wealthier counterparts, even after controlling for
    various district characteristics and state-level fixed effects.</p>
        <fig id="tbl-models">
          <caption>
            <p>Table 1: Unconditional and conditional convergence
      across districts.</p>
          </caption>
          <table-wrap>
            <table>
              <colgroup>
                <col width="13%"/>
                <col width="12%"/>
                <col width="9%"/>
                <col width="12%"/>
                <col width="12%"/>
                <col width="12%"/>
                <col width="9%"/>
                <col width="12%"/>
                <col width="12%"/>
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th/>
                  <th>Model 1</th>
                  <th/>
                  <th>Model 2</th>
                  <th/>
                  <th>Model 3</th>
                  <th/>
                  <th>Model 4</th>
                  <th/>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td/>
                  <td>OLS</td>
                  <td>SDM</td>
                  <td>OLS</td>
                  <td>SDM</td>
                  <td>OLS</td>
                  <td>SDM</td>
                  <td>OLS</td>
                  <td>SDM</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Direct</td>
                  <td>-0.020***</td>
                  <td>-0.021***</td>
                  <td>-0.022***</td>
                  <td>-0.021***</td>
                  <td>-0.025***</td>
                  <td>-0.026***</td>
                  <td>-0.025***</td>
                  <td>-0.025***</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td/>
                  <td>(0.002)</td>
                  <td>(0.002)</td>
                  <td>(0.003)</td>
                  <td>(0.002)</td>
                  <td>(0.003)</td>
                  <td>(0.002)</td>
                  <td>(0.003)</td>
                  <td>(0.002)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Indirect</td>
                  <td>–</td>
                  <td>-0.001</td>
                  <td>–</td>
                  <td>-0.001</td>
                  <td>–</td>
                  <td>-0.015*</td>
                  <td>–</td>
                  <td>-0.012*</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td/>
                  <td/>
                  <td>(0.006)</td>
                  <td/>
                  <td>(0.005)</td>
                  <td/>
                  <td>(0.008)</td>
                  <td/>
                  <td>(0.007)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Total</td>
                  <td>-0.020***</td>
                  <td>-0.022***</td>
                  <td>-0.022***</td>
                  <td>-0.022***</td>
                  <td>-0.025***</td>
                  <td>-0.041***</td>
                  <td>-0.025***</td>
                  <td>-0.037***</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td/>
                  <td>(0.002)</td>
                  <td>(0.006)</td>
                  <td>(0.003)</td>
                  <td>(0.005)</td>
                  <td>(0.003)</td>
                  <td>(0.008)</td>
                  <td>(0.003)</td>
                  <td>(0.007)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Controls</td>
                  <td>No</td>
                  <td>No</td>
                  <td>No</td>
                  <td>No</td>
                  <td>Yes</td>
                  <td>Yes</td>
                  <td>Yes</td>
                  <td>Yes</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>State FE</td>
                  <td>No</td>
                  <td>No</td>
                  <td>Yes</td>
                  <td>Yes</td>
                  <td>No</td>
                  <td>No</td>
                  <td>Yes</td>
                  <td>Yes</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>AIC</td>
                  <td>-1945</td>
                  <td>-2290</td>
                  <td>-2413</td>
                  <td>-2466</td>
                  <td>-2211</td>
                  <td>-2356</td>
                  <td>-2469</td>
                  <td>-2499</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </table-wrap>
        </fig>
        <p>Importantly, the spatial Durbin model uncovers significant
    spatial spillover effects that are masked in traditional OLS
    estimations. These indirect effects, which capture the influence of
    neighboring districts’ initial conditions on a district’s growth
    rate, become increasingly prominent and statistically significant as
    we add controls and state fixed effects to our specifications. In
    our most comprehensive model, we find a significant indirect effect
    of -0.012, suggesting that a district’s growth trajectory is
    meaningfully influenced by the initial economic conditions of its
    neighbors. This finding highlights the importance of geographical
    proximity and spatial interactions in the convergence process.</p>
        <p>The total impact of initial conditions on growth, combining both
    direct and spillover effects, is substantially larger when we
    account for spatial dependence. In our fully specified model, the
    total convergence effect in the spatial Durbin model (-0.037) is
    approximately 48% larger than the OLS estimate (-0.025). This
    difference, supported by better model fit statistics, indicates that
    conventional non-spatial approaches may significantly underestimate
    the speed of regional convergence by failing to capture the
    additional convergence channels created through spatial spillovers.
    These results emphasize that regional convergence in India operates
    not only through district-specific factors but also through
    significant spatial interactions between neighboring districts.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <sec id="better-luminosity-data-from-viirs">
        <title>Better luminosity data from VIIRS</title>
        <p>Our analysis, following Chanda and Kabiraj
    (<xref alt="2020" rid="ref-chanda_kabiraj_district_convergence" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>),
    relies on radiance-calibrated DMSP-OLS nighttime lights data
    covering the period 1996 to 2010. While this dataset has been widely
    validated as a proxy for economic activity
    (<xref alt="Henderson, Storeygard, and Weil 2012" rid="ref-henderson_storeygard_weil_lights" ref-type="bibr">Henderson,
    Storeygard, and Weil 2012</xref>;
    <xref alt="Chen and Nordhaus 2011" rid="ref-chen_nordhaus_luminosity_gdp" ref-type="bibr">Chen
    and Nordhaus 2011</xref>), DMSP-OLS data suffer from well-documented
    limitations including top-coding in bright urban cores, lack of
    on-board calibration leading to inter-satellite inconsistencies, and
    blooming artifacts that spatially blur light sources beyond their
    true boundaries
    (<xref alt="Abrahams, Oram, and Lozano-Gracia 2018" rid="ref-abrahams_etal_deblurring" ref-type="bibr">Abrahams,
    Oram, and Lozano-Gracia 2018</xref>). These measurement issues can
    attenuate the precision of convergence estimates, particularly in
    rapidly urbanizing districts where saturation may mask growth
    variation.</p>
        <p>The Visible Infrared Imaging Radiometer Suite (VIIRS) Day/Night
    Band, operational since 2012, represents a substantial improvement
    over DMSP-OLS along multiple dimensions. VIIRS offers finer spatial
    resolution (approximately 750 meters versus 2.7 kilometers),
    on-board radiometric calibration that provides consistent
    quantitative measurements, and a wider dynamic range that avoids
    saturation in urban areas while detecting dim lights in rural
    settlements
    (<xref alt="Elvidge et al. 2017" rid="ref-elvidge_etal_viirs" ref-type="bibr">Elvidge
    et al. 2017</xref>). Comparative evaluations have shown that VIIRS
    explains 10 to 15 percentage points more variation in subnational
    economic activity than DMSP-OLS
    (<xref alt="Chen and Nordhaus 2015" rid="ref-chen_nordhaus_measurement_error" ref-type="bibr">Chen
    and Nordhaus 2015</xref>), and systematic assessments recommend
    VIIRS as the preferred product for cross-sectional and recent
    time-series studies
    (<xref alt="Gibson et al. 2021" rid="ref-gibson_etal_ntl_measurement" ref-type="bibr">Gibson
    et al. 2021</xref>). Future extensions of our convergence analysis
    using VIIRS data could yield more precise estimates of both direct
    and indirect effects, particularly in districts where DMSP
    saturation may have compressed the measured distribution of
    luminosity.</p>
        <p>A practical challenge for extending long-run convergence studies
    is the discontinuity between DMSP (1992–2013) and VIIRS
    (2012–present) sensor eras. Recent harmonization efforts, notably
    the global harmonized nighttime light dataset by Li et al.
    (<xref alt="2020" rid="ref-li_etal_harmonization" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>),
    have created consistent 27-year time series by calibrating VIIRS
    observations to DMSP-equivalent units during the overlap period.
    Such harmonized datasets could enable the extension of our spatial
    Durbin analysis to more recent periods, allowing researchers to
    examine whether the convergence patterns and spatial spillovers
    documented here have persisted, accelerated, or changed in character
    as India’s economy has continued to transform.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="new-research-directions">
        <title>New research directions</title>
        <p>While our analysis documents the average convergence effect and
    its spatial spillover component, the cross-sectional regression
    framework does not capture potential heterogeneity in convergence
    patterns across the income distribution. Distribution dynamics
    approaches, as pioneered by Quah
    (<xref alt="1996" rid="ref-quah_twin_peaks" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>),
    could reveal whether Indian districts are converging to a single
    steady state or forming distinct convergence clubs where districts
    converge within groups but diverge across them. The regression tree
    methods developed by Durlauf and Johnson
    (<xref alt="1995" rid="ref-durlauf_johnson_convergence_clubs" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>)
    for identifying multiple growth regimes could be combined with
    spatial econometric techniques
    (<xref alt="Rey and Montouri 1999" rid="ref-rey_spatial_dynamics" ref-type="bibr">Rey
    and Montouri 1999</xref>) to examine whether geographic clusters of
    districts follow distinct convergence trajectories, potentially
    revealing spatial poverty traps or growth poles that are not visible
    in average convergence estimates.</p>
        <p>A second important direction concerns the causal identification
    of the spillover channels that our spatial Durbin model captures in
    reduced form. While our estimates document significant indirect
    effects, the model does not identify whether these spillovers
    operate through infrastructure linkages, labor migration, technology
    diffusion, or market access channels. Quasi-experimental approaches,
    such as those employed by Asher and Novosad
    (<xref alt="2020" rid="ref-asher_novosad_rural_roads" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>)
    to study the causal effects of rural road construction on structural
    transformation in India, could be embedded within spatial
    econometric frameworks to isolate specific spillover mechanisms.
    Understanding which channels drive the indirect convergence effects
    is critical for designing spatially targeted policies that can
    amplify positive spillovers.</p>
        <p>Third, the growing availability of diverse satellite products and
    machine learning methods opens possibilities for richer measurement
    of regional economic activity. Jean et al.
    (<xref alt="2016" rid="ref-jean_etal_poverty_prediction" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>)
    demonstrated that combining high-resolution daytime imagery with
    nighttime lights through deep learning can substantially improve
    poverty prediction in data-scarce settings. Similarly, Keola,
    Andersson, and Hall
    (<xref alt="2015" rid="ref-keola_etal_lights_poverty" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>)
    showed that integrating nighttime lights with land cover data
    improves economic measurement in agricultural areas where lights
    alone provide weak signals. As Donaldson and Storeygard
    (<xref alt="2016" rid="ref-donaldson_storeygard_remotesensing" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>)
    emphasize, the expanding ecosystem of satellite-derived
    data—including vegetation indices, built-up area detection, and
    high-frequency mobility indicators—offers opportunities to construct
    multi-dimensional proxies for regional economic activity that go
    beyond what nighttime lights alone can capture.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="research-reproducibility-and-open-science">
        <title>Research reproducibility and open science</title>
        <p>The complexity of satellite-based economic research—involving
    multi-step data processing pipelines, spatial econometric
    estimation, and geographic visualization—makes reproducibility both
    challenging and essential. As Donaldson and Storeygard
    (<xref alt="2016" rid="ref-donaldson_storeygard_remotesensing" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>)
    note, the processing of satellite data requires careful
    documentation and sharing of code to ensure that results can be
    replicated and extended. Each methodological choice in the pipeline,
    from sensor inter-calibration to spatial weight matrix construction,
    can affect empirical conclusions
    (<xref alt="Gibson et al. 2021" rid="ref-gibson_etal_ntl_measurement" ref-type="bibr">Gibson
    et al. 2021</xref>), underscoring the need for transparent
    computational workflows that allow other researchers to verify and
    build upon published findings.</p>
        <p>This article adopts a reproducible research approach through
    Quarto’s single-source publishing framework, where a single
    manuscript file generates multiple output formats—interactive HTML,
    journal PDF, and supplementary materials—from the same source. All
    computational analyses are documented in embedded notebooks that
    readers can inspect alongside the results they produce, creating a
    complete chain from raw data to published findings. The interactive
    web-based visualization tool, built on Google Earth Engine, allows
    researchers to independently explore the spatial and temporal
    patterns in the nighttime light data, facilitating verification of
    our visual findings and enabling new discoveries beyond what static
    representations can convey.</p>
        <p>Open-source tools and cloud computing platforms are rapidly
    lowering the barriers to reproducible spatial economic research.
    Cloud-based computational notebooks, such as those developed by
    Mendez and Patnaik
    (<xref alt="2024" rid="ref-mendez_patnaik_notebook" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>)
    for processing nighttime lights data, eliminate the need for
    specialized local software and provide accessible workflows for data
    ingestion, preprocessing, spatial analysis, and visualization. The
    combination of open data repositories, version-controlled code, and
    cloud computing infrastructure creates an ecosystem where the full
    analytical pipeline—from satellite imagery to econometric
    results—can be made transparent, verifiable, and extensible by the
    broader research community.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="concluding-remarks">
      <title>Concluding remarks</title>
      <p>This article examines regional convergence patterns across Indian
  districts using satellite nighttime light data, interactive
  visualizations, and spatial econometric modeling. Expanding on the
  work of Chanda and Kabiraj
  (<xref alt="2020" rid="ref-chanda_kabiraj_district_convergence" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>),
  we developed an interactive web-based visualization tool that
  illustrates spatial and convergence patterns across Indian districts.
  Spatial autocorrelation tests confirm that spatial dependence is a
  fundamental characteristic of satellite data and the regional
  convergence process in India. Estimates from our spatial Durbin model
  indicate that incorporating spatial spillovers significantly increases
  the estimated speed of regional convergence. The total convergence
  effect in our fully specified model is approximately 36% larger than
  conventional non-spatial estimates of Chanda and Kabiraj
  (<xref alt="2020" rid="ref-chanda_kabiraj_district_convergence" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>).
  This finding implies that non-spatial convergence models may
  considerably underestimate the speed of regional convergence.
  Additionally, it suggests that place-based development interventions
  may have broader impacts, as their benefits can extend to neighboring
  districts through spatial spillover effects.</p>
      <p>These results have important implications for both research
  methodology and policy design in developing countries. From a
  methodological perspective, they highlight the value of combining new
  data sources, interactive geospatial visualization tools, and spatial
  econometric methods to better understand regional economic dynamics.
  From a policy standpoint, they suggest that regional convergence
  operates not just through district-specific factors, but through
  complex spatial interactions that create additional channels for
  catch-up growth. This spatial perspective is crucial for the analysis
  and design of policies aimed at reducing regional inequalities in
  developing countries.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title/>
      <ref id="ref-adhikari_dhital_decentralization">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Adhikari</surname>
              <given-names>Bibek</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dhital</surname>
              <given-names>Ramesh</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Decentralization and regional convergence: Evidence from nighttime lights</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Development Economics</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
          <volume>145</volume>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jdeveco.2020.102467</pub-id>
          <fpage>102467</fpage>
          <lpage/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-asher_novosad_rural_roads">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Asher</surname>
              <given-names>Sam</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Novosad</surname>
              <given-names>Paul</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Rural roads and local economic development</article-title>
          <source>American Economic Review</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
          <volume>110</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1257/aer.20180268</pub-id>
          <fpage>797</fpage>
          <lpage>823</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-beyer_jain_sinha_covid">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Beyer</surname>
              <given-names>Robert C. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jain</surname>
              <given-names>Tarun</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sinha</surname>
              <given-names>Biswa N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Lights out? COVID-19 containment policies and economic activity</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Asian Economics</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
          <volume>74</volume>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.asieco.2021.101318</pub-id>
          <fpage>101318</fpage>
          <lpage/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-chakravarty_dehejia_gst">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chakravarty</surname>
              <given-names>Shankha</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dehejia</surname>
              <given-names>Rajeev</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The GST and regional divergence in india: A nightlights perspective</article-title>
          <source>Economic and Political Weekly</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <issue>42</issue>
          <fpage>47</fpage>
          <lpage>54</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-chanda_cook_demonetization">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chanda</surname>
              <given-names>Areendam</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cook</surname>
              <given-names>Justin</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Demonetization and its redistributive effects: Evidence from india</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Development Economics</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year>
          <volume>156</volume>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jdeveco.2022.102835</pub-id>
          <fpage>102835</fpage>
          <lpage/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-chanda_kabiraj_district_convergence">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chanda</surname>
              <given-names>Areendam</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kabiraj</surname>
              <given-names>Shankha</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Shedding light on regional growth and convergence in india</article-title>
          <source>World Development</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
          <volume>133</volume>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.worlddev.2020.104961</pub-id>
          <fpage>104961</fpage>
          <lpage/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-cook_shah_nregs">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cook</surname>
              <given-names>Justin</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shah</surname>
              <given-names>Manisha</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Aggregate effects from public works: Evidence from india</article-title>
          <source>Review of Economics and Statistics</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year>
          <volume>104</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1162/rest_a_00951</pub-id>
          <fpage>201</fpage>
          <lpage>217</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-ertur_koch_spatial_growth">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ertur</surname>
              <given-names>Cem</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koch</surname>
              <given-names>Wilfried</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Growth, technological interdependence and spatial externalities: Theory and evidence</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Applied Econometrics</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jae.963</pub-id>
          <fpage>1033</fpage>
          <lpage>1062</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-fischer_spatial_mrw">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fischer</surname>
              <given-names>Manfred M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A spatial mankiw-romer-weil model: Theory and evidence</article-title>
          <source>Annals of Regional Science</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00168-010-0384-6</pub-id>
          <fpage>419</fpage>
          <lpage>436</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-gennaioli_etal_growth_regions">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gennaioli</surname>
              <given-names>Nicola</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>La Porta</surname>
              <given-names>Rafael</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lopez-de-Silanes</surname>
              <given-names>Florencio</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shleifer</surname>
              <given-names>Andrei</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Growth in regions</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Economic Growth</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10887-014-9105-9</pub-id>
          <fpage>259</fpage>
          <lpage>309</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-henderson_storeygard_weil_lights">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Henderson</surname>
              <given-names>J. Vernon</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Storeygard</surname>
              <given-names>Adam</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weil</surname>
              <given-names>David N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Measuring economic growth from outer space</article-title>
          <source>American Economic Review</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year>
          <volume>102</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1257/aer.102.2.994</pub-id>
          <fpage>994</fpage>
          <lpage>1028</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-jha_talathi_colonial_india">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jha</surname>
              <given-names>Saumitra</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Talathi</surname>
              <given-names>Anand</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Colonial institutions and long-run development in india: Evidence from nightlights</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Development Economics</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
          <volume>153</volume>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jdeveco.2021.102726</pub-id>
          <fpage>102726</fpage>
          <lpage/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-lessmann_seidel_regional_inequality">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lessmann</surname>
              <given-names>Christian</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seidel</surname>
              <given-names>André</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Regional inequality, convergence, and its determinants: A view from outer space</article-title>
          <source>European Economic Review</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
          <volume>92</volume>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.euroecorev.2016.11.009</pub-id>
          <fpage>110</fpage>
          <lpage>132</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-pinkovskiy_salaimartin_lights_poverty">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pinkovskiy</surname>
              <given-names>Maxim</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sala-i-Martin</surname>
              <given-names>Xavier</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Lights, camera, income! Illuminating the national accounts-household surveys debate</article-title>
          <source>Quarterly Journal of Economics</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year>
          <volume>131</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/qje/qjw003</pub-id>
          <fpage>579</fpage>
          <lpage>631</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-abrahams_etal_deblurring">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Abrahams</surname>
              <given-names>Alexei</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oram</surname>
              <given-names>Christopher</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lozano-Gracia</surname>
              <given-names>Nancy</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Deblurring DMSP nighttime lights: A new method using gaussian filters and frequencies of illumination</article-title>
          <source>Remote Sensing of Environment</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
          <volume>210</volume>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rse.2018.03.018</pub-id>
          <fpage>242</fpage>
          <lpage>258</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-chen_nordhaus_luminosity_gdp">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>Xi</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nordhaus</surname>
              <given-names>William D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Using luminosity data as a proxy for economic statistics</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year>
          <volume>108</volume>
          <issue>21</issue>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1017031108</pub-id>
          <fpage>8589</fpage>
          <lpage>8594</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-donaldson_storeygard_remotesensing">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Donaldson</surname>
              <given-names>Dave</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Storeygard</surname>
              <given-names>Adam</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The view from above: Applications of satellite data in economics</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Economic Perspectives</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1257/jep.30.4.171</pub-id>
          <fpage>171</fpage>
          <lpage>198</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-elvidge_etal_viirs">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Elvidge</surname>
              <given-names>Christopher D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baugh</surname>
              <given-names>Kimberly E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhizhin</surname>
              <given-names>Mikhail</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hsu</surname>
              <given-names>Feng-Chi</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ghosh</surname>
              <given-names>Tilottama</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>VIIRS night-time lights</article-title>
          <source>International Journal of Remote Sensing</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <issue>21</issue>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01431161.2017.1342050</pub-id>
          <fpage>5860</fpage>
          <lpage>5879</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-gibson_etal_ntl_measurement">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gibson</surname>
              <given-names>John</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Olivia</surname>
              <given-names>Susan</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boe-Gibson</surname>
              <given-names>Geua</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>Chao</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Which night lights data should we use in economics, and where?</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Development Economics</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
          <volume>149</volume>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jdeveco.2020.102602</pub-id>
          <fpage>102602</fpage>
          <lpage/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-chen_nordhaus_measurement_error">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>Xi</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nordhaus</surname>
              <given-names>William D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A test of the new VIIRS lights data set: Population and economic output in africa</article-title>
          <source>Remote Sensing</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/rs70404937</pub-id>
          <fpage>4937</fpage>
          <lpage>4947</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-mendez_patnaik_notebook">
        <element-citation>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mendez</surname>
              <given-names>Carlos</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Patnaik</surname>
              <given-names>Ayush</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A python notebook for processing nighttime lights data: Methods and applications</article-title>
          <publisher-name>GitHub Repository</publisher-name>
          <year iso-8601-date="2024">2024</year>
          <uri>https://github.com/example/ntl-notebook</uri>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-li_etal_harmonization">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>Xi</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>Yuyu</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhao</surname>
              <given-names>Min</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhao</surname>
              <given-names>Xia</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A harmonized global nighttime light dataset 1992–2018</article-title>
          <source>Scientific Data</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41597-020-0510-y</pub-id>
          <fpage>168</fpage>
          <lpage/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-jean_etal_poverty_prediction">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jean</surname>
              <given-names>Neal</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Burke</surname>
              <given-names>Marshall</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xie</surname>
              <given-names>Michael</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Davis</surname>
              <given-names>W. Matthew</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lobell</surname>
              <given-names>David B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ermon</surname>
              <given-names>Stefano</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Combining satellite imagery and machine learning to predict poverty</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year>
          <volume>353</volume>
          <issue>6301</issue>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aaf7894</pub-id>
          <fpage>790</fpage>
          <lpage>794</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-rey_spatial_dynamics">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rey</surname>
              <given-names>Sergio J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Montouri</surname>
              <given-names>Brett D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>US regional income convergence: A spatial econometric perspective</article-title>
          <source>Regional Studies</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="1999">1999</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00343409950122945</pub-id>
          <fpage>143</fpage>
          <lpage>156</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-quah_twin_peaks">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Quah</surname>
              <given-names>Danny T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Twin peaks: Growth and convergence in models of distribution dynamics</article-title>
          <source>Economic Journal</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="1996">1996</year>
          <volume>106</volume>
          <issue>437</issue>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2235377</pub-id>
          <fpage>1045</fpage>
          <lpage>1055</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-durlauf_johnson_convergence_clubs">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Durlauf</surname>
              <given-names>Steven N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Johnson</surname>
              <given-names>Paul A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Multiple regimes and cross-country growth behaviour</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Applied Econometrics</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="1995">1995</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jae.3950100404</pub-id>
          <fpage>365</fpage>
          <lpage>384</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-keola_etal_lights_poverty">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Keola</surname>
              <given-names>Souknilanh</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andersson</surname>
              <given-names>Magnus</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hall</surname>
              <given-names>Ola</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Monitoring economic development from space: Using nighttime light and land cover data to measure economic growth</article-title>
          <source>World Development</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year>
          <volume>66</volume>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.worlddev.2014.08.017</pub-id>
          <fpage>322</fpage>
          <lpage>334</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="fn1">
        <label>1</label>
        <p>Following Chanda and Kabiraj
    (<xref alt="2020" rid="ref-chanda_kabiraj_district_convergence" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>),
    our sample consists of 520 districts (out of a possible 593). There
    were 593 districts in 2001, which rose to 640 districts in the 2011
    census. To match the districts among two census files, we summed up
    the curved-out districts with their origin districts in the 2011
    census files. Eight districts among 47 new districts were created by
    curving out some areas from multiple districts. Those new districts
    along with their multiple-origin districts were dropped from our
    sample. We dropped all the districts in the state of Assam where
    more than 50% of districts were created in that manner.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn2">
        <label>2</label>
        <p>The Interactive web application is available at
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bit.ly/india-rc-ntl">https://bit.ly/india-rc-ntl</ext-link>.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn3">
        <label>3</label>
        <p>The data is taken from a report by the Economic
    Advisory Council to the Prime Minister (EAC-PM), released on
    September 18, 2024.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
  </back>
  <!-- (F2ED4C6E)[nb-1]:/Users/carlos/GitHub/project2025s/notebooks/c01_view_from_space.qmd -->
  <!-- (F2ED4C6E)[nb-2]:/Users/carlos/GitHub/project2025s/notebooks/c02_regional_convergence_sc.qmd -->
  <!-- (F2ED4C6E)[nb-3]:/Users/carlos/GitHub/project2025s/notebooks/c03_spatial_dependence_lisa.ipynb -->
  <!-- (F2ED4C6E)[nb-4]:/Users/carlos/GitHub/project2025s/notebooks/c04_spillover_modeling_6nn.ipynb -->
</article>
